<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Seaven sermons.  [sermons 1 and 2 only] preached vpon severall occasions. Viz. 1 The Christians prayer for the Churches peace. One sermon on Psal. 122.6. 2 One sermon on 1 Sam. 2.30 3 Baruchs sore gently opened; Gods salve skilfully applyed. In two sermons on Jeremy 45.5. 4 The araignement of coveteousnesse. In three sermons on Luke 12.15. By John Stoughton, Doctor in Divinitie, late of Aldermanburie, London.</title>
            <title>Sermons. Selected sermons</title>
            <author>Stoughton, John, d. 1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23311_PARTIAL</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853048</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7995</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Seaven sermons.  [sermons 1 and 2 only] preached vpon severall occasions. Viz. 1 The Christians prayer for the Churches peace. One sermon on Psal. 122.6. 2 One sermon on 1 Sam. 2.30 3 Baruchs sore gently opened; Gods salve skilfully applyed. In two sermons on Jeremy 45.5. 4 The araignement of coveteousnesse. In three sermons on Luke 12.15. By John Stoughton, Doctor in Divinitie, late of Aldermanburie, London.</title>
                  <title>Sermons. Selected sermons</title>
                  <author>Stoughton, John, d. 1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 37, [5], 49-76; [8], 55, [1]; [8], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J[ohn] D[awson and Richard Badger] for John Bellamie, and Ralph Smith, and are to be sold at their shop, at the three Golden-Lyons in Cornhill neere the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue, with added general title page and conjugate blank, of "The Christians prayer for the Churches peace" (printed by John Dawson), "Baruch's sore gently opened; God's salve skilfully applied" (printed by Richard Badger), and "The arraignement of covetousnesse" (printed by Richard Badger). In the first part, "A sermon upon 1 Sam, 2.30" has separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>¹F4 is cancelled.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Part 1: p. 34-35: print missing. Some print faded and show-through and some pages stained. P. 30-end of part 3 of the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7995:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7995:1"/>
            <p>SEAVEN SERMONS, PREACHED UPON Severall Occaſions.</p>
            <p>VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The Christians Prayer for the Churches Peace.</hi> One Sermon on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6.</item>
                  <item>2 One Sermon on 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30</item>
                  <item>3 BARUCHS <hi>Sore gently opened;</hi> GODS <hi>Salve skilfully applyed.</hi> In two Sermons on <hi>Jeremy</hi> 45.5.</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>The Araignement of Coveteouſneſſe.</hi> In three Sermons on <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 15.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN STOUGHTON, Doctor in Divinitie, late of <hi>Aldermanburie, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J.D.</hi> for <hi>John Bellamie,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop, at the three <hi>Golden-Lyons</hi> in <hi>Cornhill</hi> neere the <hi>Royall-Exchange.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE CHRISTIANS PRAYER FOR THE CHVRCHES PEACE.</p>
                  <p>OR, A SERMON VPON PSAL. 122. ver. 6.</p>
                  <p>Preached at Mercers Chappell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> JOHN STOVOHTON. Doctor in Divinity, late of <hi>Alderman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>PSAL. 137. 5. <hi>If I forget thee oh Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vult Deus rogari, vult quadom importunitate vinci bona hac violentia eſt, qua Deus non offenditur ſed placatur:</hi> Gregori: in ſext. Pſal. Poenitent.</p>
                  <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>John Dawſon,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop, at the three golden Lions in <hi>Cormbill</hi> neere the Royall Exchange, 1640.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE widow of the deceaſed Author in Teſtimony of her humble and thankefull acknowledgement of the reſpect ſhewed to her Dearest Husband, preſenteth theſe enſuing Sermons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:4"/>
                  <head>A Methodicall <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall things contained in the Sermon upon the 122. <hi>Pſalm. 6. vers.</hi> as it was perfected by the <hi>Author,</hi> and left written with his own hand.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Context.
<list>
                           <item>1 Tryumphant joy concerning the Churches,
<list>
                                 <item>1 Portion,</item>
                                 <item>2 Cheife perfection.</item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 Sublimity. Torrent of affection, r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>. <hi>ver.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Solidity. Fountaine of Reaſon, 2. <hi>ver.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 the beauty of it,</item>
                                 <item>2 His proprietie in it,</item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 It is the place of Gods Worſhip.</item>
                                 <item>2 There is the company of Saints.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Ardens deſire.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Torrent of affection,
<list>
                                       <item>1 Precepts for prayer, 6. <hi>ver.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Preſcript forms, <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Fountaine of Reaſon, for
<list>
                                       <item>1 Brethren, 8. <hi>verſ.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Father, the houſe of our God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Text.
<list>
                           <item>1 Amandate,</item>
                           <item>2 A motive.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſervation.</hi> It is the duty of all Chriſtians to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to provoke others to doe the like: and all their owne good depends upon it.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Explication.
<list>
                           <item>1 Propoſition.
<list>
                                 <item>1 For whom: Ieruſalem.
<list>
                                       <pb facs="tcp:7995:4"/>
                                       <item>1 Incluſively.
<list>
                                             <item>1 Myſtical either
<list>
                                                   <item>1 general the Church
<list>
                                                         <item>True.</item>
                                                         <item>Vulverſal</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>2 ſpecial: the members
<list>
                                                         <item>Naturall.</item>
                                                         <item>morenoble</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>3 Singular.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Literall.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Excluſively.
<list>
                                       <item>1 Our own Church.</item>
                                       <item>2 Principals in it
<list>
                                             <item>Citties.</item>
                                             <item>Vniverſities</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>What: Place. in
<list>
                                       <item>1 Generall Latitude.
<list>
                                             <item>1 Protection
<list>
                                                   <item>Preſervation,</item>
                                                   <item>Liberation.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2 Perfection
<list>
                                                   <item>Reſtauration,</item>
                                                   <item>Purgation.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>3 Propagation to
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Inſidels,</item>
                                                   <item>Heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                         <desc>•</desc>
                                                      </gap>cks.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Speceall proprietie. Peace, with the
<list>
                                             <item>Lord,</item>
                                             <item>Cityes,</item>
                                             <item>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>mies.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 How
<list>
                                       <item>1 Sct: to
<list>
                                             <item>1 Pray,</item>
                                             <item>2 Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>ite.
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Endeavours,
<list>
                                                         <item>1 Councels,</item>
                                                         <item>2 Aides.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>2 Wiſhes.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Manner: with
<list>
                                             <item>1 Sinceritie,</item>
                                             <item>2 Zeale,</item>
                                             <item>3 Conſtancie.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 Who: the Chriſtian
<list>
                                       <item>1 True, All: of what
<list>
                                             <item>Station ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>ever.
<list>
                                                   <item>Magiſtrate, ſubject</item>
                                                   <item>Miniſter, people.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2 Condition.
<list>
                                                   <pb facs="tcp:7995:5"/>
                                                   <item>Learned, unlearned</item>
                                                   <item>Man, woman.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Probation.
<list>
                                 <item>1. Scripture.
<list>
                                       <item>1 Teſtimonies,</item>
                                       <item>2 Examples.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Nature of
<list>
                                       <item>1. Jeruſalem, the
<list>
                                             <item>1 Spouſe of Chriſt.</item>
                                             <item>2 Mother of Chriſtians</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2. Peace: The ſumme of bleſſings.
<list>
                                             <item>1 Mother of Proſperitie,</item>
                                             <item>2 Nurſe of Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>3. Prayer,
<list>
                                             <item>1. Efficacie,</item>
                                             <item>2. Neceſſitie.
<list>
                                                   <item>1 God rules the world,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Prayer God, for
<list>
                                                         <item>1 Peace,</item>
                                                         <item>2 Ieruſalem.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>4. Chriſtian. Who is a debtor of all theſe duties, as he is a
<list>
                                             <item>1 Sonne of
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Ieruſalem,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Peace,</item>
                                                   <item>3 Prayer.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2 Lord, and ſo able.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Appl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ation.
<list>
                           <item>1. Convi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>tion. Reprehenſion of
<list>
                                 <item>1 Evill doers,</item>
                                 <item>2 Doers of impertinent things,</item>
                                 <item>3 Doers of nothing.
<list>
                                       <item>Such as are
<list>
                                             <item>1 Not for Ieruſalem, but Babell.</item>
                                             <item>2 Not for peace, but deſtruction.</item>
                                             <item>3 Not importune heaven, but councell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                                   <desc>••</desc>
                                                </gap>ell.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. Examination.</item>
                                 <item>3. Exhortation.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <pb facs="tcp:7995:5"/>
                           <item>1 Dutyes.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1 Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>rall, pray in
<list>
                                             <item>1 Faith,</item>
                                             <item>2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                                                   <desc>•••</desc>
                                                </gap>tie,</item>
                                             <item>3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                                   <desc>••</desc>
                                                </gap>pentane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Speci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ll.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>1 Pray for Ieruſalem.
<list>
                                       <item>1 Proſperiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>
                                          <list>
                                             <item>1 Protection,
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Conſervation,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Liberation.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2 Perfection,
<list>
                                                   <item>1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                                         <desc>••</desc>
                                                      </gap>gation,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                                                         <desc>•••</desc>
                                                      </gap>uration.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>3 Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••••</desc>
                                                </gap>
                                                <list>
                                                   <item>1 Gentiles,</item>
                                                   <item>2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                                         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                                      </gap>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Peace with
<list>
                                             <item>1 Ene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••</desc>
                                                </gap>,</item>
                                             <item>2 City<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>s,</item>
                                             <item>3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                                   <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                                </gap>.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Excite others
<list>
                                       <item>1 All in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                                             <desc>•••••</desc>
                                          </gap>ly, either by
<list>
                                             <item>Studies.
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Councels,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Helpes.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>Wiſhes.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                             <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                          </gap>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>r. by
<list>
                                 <item>1 Strong faith,</item>
                                 <item>2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                                       <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 Fruitfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4. Inſtancy. Prayer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                                       <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1 Intention of deſire.</item>
                                       <item>2 Vigour of zeale in the wiſhes of
<list>
                                             <item>1 All ſingular,</item>
                                             <item>2 All conjoyned.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>5. Conſtancy.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Helpes.
<list>
                           <item>1 MM<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>s.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Depoſe carnall ſecuritie,</item>
                                 <item>2 Lay things to heart,</item>
                                 <item>3 Take heed of the world.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Motives.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Texeuall. in
<list>
                                       <pb facs="tcp:7995:6"/>
                                       <item>1. Command<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                                          <list>
                                             <item>1 God requires it,</item>
                                             <item>2 Godly ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••••</desc>
                                                </gap>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>3 The Church inju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••••</desc>
                                                </gap>,</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Motive
<list>
                                             <item>1 Neceſſitie of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••</desc>
                                                </gap>,</item>
                                             <item>2 Societie of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••</desc>
                                                </gap>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>3 Communitie of Honor
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                         <desc>•</desc>
                                                      </gap>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>2 to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                                                         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                                                      </gap>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Additionall.
<list>
                                       <item>1 A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                             <desc>••</desc>
                                          </gap>ighty matter is agitated,
<list>
                                             <item>1 The Church of God,</item>
                                             <item>2 Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>agog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap>ue of Sathan.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Our owne good is agitated.
<list>
                                             <item>1 Communion of good,</item>
                                             <item>2 Contagion of evill.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>3 Article of time is instan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>.
<list>
                                             <item>1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                                                   <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                                </gap>; infirme for
<list>
                                                   <item>Weapons,</item>
                                                   <item>Courage.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2 En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                                                   <desc>••••</desc>
                                                </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                                                   <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                                </gap>; Proud of
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Aides,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Policies.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>4 Succeſſe of worke incites.
<list>
                                             <item>1 From certaine promiſe made,</item>
                                             <item>2 Joyfull from duty performed.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Ornament of prayer invites.
<list>
                                             <item>1 Smalleſt impenſe,</item>
                                             <item>2 Greateſt compenſation,</item>
                                             <item>3 Fonleſt offence.
<list>
                                                   <item>1 Perfidiouſneſſe,</item>
                                                   <item>2 Ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                                         <desc>•</desc>
                                                      </gap>mie.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:6"/>
                  <head>THE CHRISTIANS PRAYER FOR THE CHVRCHES PEACE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>PSAL. 122. 6.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, they ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper that love thee.</p>
                        <p>Or as ſome tranſlations read it:</p>
                        <p>O pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, let them proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that love thee.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole Pſalme brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth nothing but a ſweete perfume of inflamed affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: to God, and to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> ſuch as that onely bird, the dying Phoenix, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her bed of ſpices (all the ſpices of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7995:7"/> 
                     <hi>Arabia)</hi> and fired with the pure beames of the Sun, cannot paralell.</p>
                  <p>The only Paralell may be the Angell in <hi>Revel.</hi> chap. 8. verſe 3. <hi>Having a golden cenſer in his hand, and much odours given unto him, to offer with the prayers of all Saints, vpon the golden altar before the Throne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which the ancient legends report of <hi>Jgnatius,</hi> that when he was dead, the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> was found written in his heart in golden Characters. And that which our moderne ſtories relate of <hi>Queene Mary:</hi> that ſhe ſhould ſay, if they did open her when ſhee was dead; they ſhould find <hi>Callis</hi> lying at her heart: the loſſe (it ſeemes) of which haſtened her end.</p>
                  <p>Theſe may be, nay are truely verified in <hi>David</hi> here. In whoſe heart you may ſee the loue God, and of the Church of God; deepely ingraven in legible and indelable characters. For we have here a double tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of <hi>living affections,</hi> each of them fedde with a <hi>double ſpring of Reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The firſt is an <hi>affection of Triumphant joy,</hi> and <hi>delight;</hi> in the apprehenſion of the perfect beauty of the Church, and his part and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in it. Not long agoe (one pſalme one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly between) his ſoule was withered within his breaſt, as the water trees in the Drought, as it were blaſted with the ſad thoughts of his baniſhment: <hi>Woe is me that I dwell in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7995:7"/> that my habitation is in the tents of Kedar:</hi> but now his joy flouriſheth againe, in the thoughts of an approaching returne: reviue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) <hi>like a dry tree, by the ſent of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob 14. 8. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>the waters,</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes) and breaking forth into this extacy of divine affections, (in the beginning of the Pſalme.) <hi>I was glad when they ſaid unto mee, let vs goe into the houſe of the Lord: our feete ſhall ſtand within thy gates, O Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Now the <hi>ſpring of reaſon,</hi> that fed this ſtrong affection in him: are thoſe Two, that the Philoſophers give, as the juſt cauſe of all good affections:</p>
                  <p>There are two things, that make us loue any thing:</p>
                  <p>1. The beauty of it. 2. The propriety of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The beauty of the Church, ſet his heart ſo much in love with it; that is expreſſed in the 3. verſe. <hi>Ieruſalem is built as a City com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact together.</hi> How ever other mens eyes looked ſcornefully vpon <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> as have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no beauty, nor comlines in it: yet the godly man ſeeth, (of all the ſocieties in the world) no ſuch beauty, as in the Church of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>his propriety</hi> hee hath in it, or the relation in which he ſtandeth to it, which is Double, 1. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in the fourth verſe) is the place of Gods worſhip, <hi>whether the Tribes goe up: the Tribes of the Lord, to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7995:8"/> to praiſe the Name of the Lord.</hi> There was the <hi>beauty,</hi> becauſe there was the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, the fountaine of all beauty. And there is his ſecond relation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, in that there was the company of all the Saints of God; <hi>there hee ſet thrones for the houſe of David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> And then he commeth to his ſecond af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which is anſwerable to the other: and but a counter-pane of it, (his loue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it ſelfe in both) and that is: his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire for the good of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the verſe that I haue read. And this ardent deſire breaketh forth, and expreſſeth it ſelfe in a double ſtreame. We haue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt a precept for prayer, in the verſe read, <hi>Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And then a <hi>preſcript forme of prayer,</hi> for peace in the next verſe: <hi>Peace be within thy walls,</hi> and <hi>proſperity within thy palluces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> And then, the <hi>ſprings of reaſon,</hi> that feed this loving affection of deſire, and maketh it in continuall motion, are anſwerable to the former.</p>
                  <p>He lookes upon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the double relation mentioned before. 1 <hi>For my Brethren and companions ſake, I will now ſay, Peace bee unto thee.</hi> There is the firſt relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And the ſecond is: <hi>For the houſe of our God,</hi>
                     <hi>I will procure thy good,</hi> in the laſt verſe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I have given you in briefe the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7995:8"/> whole ſumme of the Pſalme.</p>
                  <p>But to returne to the verſe: There be two things obſervable in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Mandate,</hi> and</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Motive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Mandate: Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Motiue,</hi> to put us upon it: <hi>They ſhall proſper that loue thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In either of theſe, there may be 3. things obſervable:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>There cannot be a better imployment for Chriſtians then Prayer. Pray</hi> for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>wee cannot aime at a better bleſsing in Prayer, then Peace.</hi> Pray for the <hi>peace</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>There is not a nearer relation wee haue to any, for whom we ſhould wiſh all good, then to Ieruſalem,</hi> pray for the peace of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the direct gradation of the verſe, but I ſhall handle it in a retrogradation: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the laſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>The neareſt relation a Chriſtian hath to any for whom he ſhould wiſh all good, is to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> pray for <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The <hi>greateſt bleſsing is Peace,</hi> pray for the <hi>peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>The moſt effectuall meanes to gaine peace is, Prayer. Pray</hi> for the peace of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7995:9"/>
                  <p>There bee as many things obſervable in the ſecond branch of the text. The motiue, that is uſed. <hi>Let them proſper that love thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>wee cannot but pray for Ieruſalem, if we love her,</hi> it is an argument wee loue not the Church of God, and the honour of God; if we will not doe ſo much as ſet forward her peace by prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There is a ſecond thing too, implied in the other tranſlation, <hi>Let them proſper that love thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our praying for the Church, giveth us a ſhare in all the Churches prayers,</hi> we haue a venture in every ſhip of prayer, that maketh a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age for heaven, if our hearts bee willing to pray for the Church, and if not, we haue no ſhare in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, <hi>All our proſperity depends upon the proſperity of the Church,</hi> and our deſires for the proſperity of it. They ſhall proſper.</p>
                  <p>It is a certaine thing, all that loue the Church of God, ſhall proſper: and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity only belongs to them, and there cannot be more effectuall inducements to perſwade men to this duty then theſe are.</p>
                  <p>I know there be ſo many ſands in the Text that ſhould I obſerve them all, the glaſſe would out-run me. I ſhall therefore contract all into one obſervation, and ſo proſecute it in many particulars briefly, that ſo I may comprehend the maine of the text, and ſhall propound it thus:
<q>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:7995:9"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>
                              <label type="milestone">
                                 <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                              </label> It is the duty of all Chriſtians, to pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, and to provoke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to doe the like: and all their owne good depends vpon it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the opening of the point, to bee very briefe in it, there bee two things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Object,</hi> that I ſhall giue a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement to, (to take the full meaning of the point.) And alſo two branches concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>act,</hi> which is to be performed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is a double Object. 1. For whom</hi> wee muſt pray for peace, that is, <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> 2. And what wee muſt pray for, for <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> that is, <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I muſt expreſſe briefly what is meant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And what is meant by <hi>Peace,</hi> which are the objects of our prayer.</p>
                  <p>I. <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (to expreſſe it in a word) there may be a double ſignification of it, which may come within the compaſſe of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of all, <hi>Ieruſalem Myſticall.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Ieruſalem Literall.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Ieruſalem Myſticall,</hi> is the <hi>Church of God,</hi> or in Generall, the common, and <hi>publike</hi> good, and welfare, which every one ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre before his owne <hi>private,</hi> and not mind ſo much his owne cabbin as the ſhip in which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7995:10"/> all proſper, or periſh together.</p>
                  <p>But more particularly to expreſſe it, you may take it in theſe three rankes, or degrees.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in the vtmoſt generallity, <hi>the true Church of God,</hi> is the object of our prayers, and the <hi>whole Church</hi> of God, every part, and po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of it: every branch and member of it throughout the world, a Chriſtian ſhould haue an inlarged affection, to reach, and comprehend, the good of all in his prayers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, and more ſpecially. Thoſe <hi>members of the Church that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mminent,</hi> the <hi>naturall members,</hi> and the <hi>noble</hi> members. The <hi>naturall members,</hi> that are the living ſtones of the building of God, not onely in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion of religion, pleaſing to God (Chriſtians in name) but thoſe that are real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch. And eſpecially ſuch as are more <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble members;</hi> that are more inſtrumentall, and organicall: the good of the Church depends more vpon them.</p>
                  <p>Such as are <hi>Eminent in power,</hi> in <hi>place,</hi> in <hi>worth,</hi> and in <hi>ſervice,</hi> our prayers muſt reach to all the Church, and to all the members of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, and more particularly, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, <hi>our owne Church,</hi> which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to, and the <hi>principalls</hi> of it: as <hi>Cities, and Vniverſities;</hi> thoſe which wee haue a peculiar relation to, doe challenge a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar ſhare in our prayers.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:7995:10"/>II. And not onely the <hi>Myſticall Ieruſalem,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Literall Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould be no ſtranger to a Chriſtians prayers; <hi>Returne, returne, O S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Wee ſhould pray for the <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ring</hi> of the people of God; even for the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> and for the <hi>ſetting vp of the new Ieruſalem;</hi> as God hath promiſed in his word.</p>
                  <p>I will onely adde one thing in this. As theſe are all <hi>included</hi> in this Ieruſalem, which we are to pray for: So by the ſame reaſon by which theſe are included, we muſt alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand there is an <hi>excluſion,</hi> and collatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a praying againſt them that are againſt <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Againſt <hi>Babel,</hi> againſt all the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for it is with <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and the enemies of it, as with a paire of ballances; when one ſcale is up, the other muſt needs, be downe; and when the one is downe, the other is vp: if <hi>Babel</hi> get alo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth low, and if <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> riſe, <hi>Babel</hi> muſt fall. So that the ſame prayers that are directed for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> perpendicularly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> that way; will alſo collaterally reach againſt <hi>Babel.</hi> And ſo I have expreſſed as much as I intended in this firſt part of the Object, which is comprehended in <hi>Ieruſalem. Pray for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>II. But <hi>what</hi> muſt we pray for, in the behalfe of <hi>Jeruſalem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> It is expreſſed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in one word, but the word i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> very comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue it is <hi>Peace.</hi> And <hi>Peace</hi> comprehends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7995:11"/> the boſome of it all bleſſings, it is the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew phraſe, when they would wiſh all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, whatſoever that commeth within the compaſſe of making happy, then they ſay <hi>Peace be to this houſe,</hi> that is, all happines be to it, and in this reſpect there may be given a double ſence of this word, <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt in the generall <hi>latitude</hi> of it,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in the more <hi>ſpeciall propriety of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the generall latitude of it: <hi>all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> and <hi>proprieties:</hi> all that is good and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and tends to the welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is comprehended under peace which we muſt pray for here.</p>
                  <p>As to giue an inſtance in two or three things. We muſt pray for the <hi>protection</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that God will protect his Church, <hi>delivering</hi> thoſe that are in danger, and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> from danger thoſe that are out of it: wee muſt pray for the <hi>perfection</hi> of the Church: that God will reſtore thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that are over-runne, and will-<hi>refine</hi> and purge more and more to all purity, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, thoſe Churches that ſtand: we muſt pray for the <hi>propagation</hi> of the Church of God, that God will ſtretch the bounds, and enlarge the borders of it, and carry the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell further, that he will bring more ſubjects to acknowledge the kingdome of Chriſt, and to ſubmit to his ſcepter, whether among the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7995:11"/> 
                     <hi>heathen</hi> of the world: or among thoſe <hi>erring</hi> people, that haue a name of chriſtianity, and yet raſe the foundation of it, that God would <hi>inlarge</hi> the borders of his Church, and <hi>inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> them. So much for the generall latitude of the word.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To take it in the <hi>propriety of it:</hi> the word <hi>Peace,</hi> in it ſelfe is an excellent bleſſing, and of ſpeciall conſequence, which our hearts ſhould pray to God, to beſtow upon his Church, either preſerving peace where it is, or beſtowing it where it is not.</p>
                  <p>A threefold peace, we ſhould pray for.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A <hi>Peace with God,</hi> in cauſing his Churches to keepe their peace with him, in walking in the <hi>purity,</hi> and <hi>power of his ordinances,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which though they were at peace with all the world, yet all will come to nothing, if religion be defiled and polluted.</p>
                  <p>As the Cardinall made it his Embleme, a <hi>Beach-tree,</hi> with this inſcription, <hi>Take off the top, and it is the ruine of all the reſt:</hi> The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that tree is ſuch, that if the top of it be cut off, it will never thrive. So it is true of the purity of religion, tamper with that, take away that, defile, and pollute that, and all other bleſſings will be gone, they will take themſelves to their wings, except there be ſomething to ſoder us with God, which can be nothing but our exact walking with him in his ordinances. Except we keepe our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7995:12"/> peace with God, all other peace will fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>As that great Artificer, who ſometime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> famous buckler for <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of the <hi>Atheni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e contrived it ſo, that hee wrought his owne name in the Center of the Buckler, which was ſo framed of ſeverall pieces, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>s, that it was impoſſible to picke out his name, who was the author of it, but the whole buckler would fall in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. So, the name of God, and the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of God, is ſuch a ſupporter to the world, that if that be ſleighted, and trampled upon: if you goe about to overthrow that all other bleſſings will fall in pieces,</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As Peace with God, ſo alſo <hi>peace among the Citizens,</hi> civill peace, free from diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion, diviſions, and diſtractions, that they may thinke the ſame things, and goe the ſame way and vnanimouſly minde the glory of the Lord together, the breach and loſſe of which Peace i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one of the greateſt miſchiefes, and miſeries, that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efall us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And a <hi>forreigne peace alſo,</hi> from all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition without, that there may be no hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, no invaſion of fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine enemies upon the Churches of God. Theſe I ſuppoſe are the principalls that comprehend the ſumme of what is meant, and couched under the name of Peace.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall onely adde one thing in this; and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7995:12"/> that is: If wee thinke onely of temporall peace, and the bleſſings upon that, it is not worth the while on pray: for peace to the Churches of God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> proſper in warre, and miſery. For as the Father com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, In the time, <hi>when they flouriſhed, they all decayed,</hi> and the vigour of religion was gone, but when they <hi>had no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they <hi>flouriſhed in religion.</hi> The primitive Church which was perſecuted by the red Dragon, was <hi>cloathed with the Sun,</hi> and <hi>crowned with a crown of twelue Stars, with the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> vnder her foot:</hi> but <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in the 17. of the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> was <hi>cloathed with ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>let, and gold,</hi> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ward riches, but no heauenly ornament about her.</p>
                  <p>Thus it may fall ſo out, that to aske onely for a temporall peace may not be worth the while: therefore you muſt ioyne in your prayers; <hi>Peace that may be ſanctified,</hi> that we may make a good vſe of it, and ſo it is very vſefull for the worke of the Goſpell, and it is a great bleſſing to inioy it.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall expreſſe brie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ch of the point, which is the <hi>office of a Chriſtian, in</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">II.</note> 
                     <hi>regard of the Act.</hi> There is a double Act, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in the point, and contained in the Text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is our duty to <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Peace,</hi> for our mother <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And it is our duty, not onely to pray our ſelues, but we muſt <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and provoke</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:7995:13"/> ſo to doe, rouze, and awaken others, to joyn in prayer, for the peace of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Now, when I ſay we are bound to pray; there are 2. other things included in that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as Prayer which is the maine thing.</p>
                  <p>There is one thing implyed inwardly; that our hearts ſhould worke to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> our pulſes beate that way, <hi>our deſires,</hi> and wiſhes, ſhould be for it. For prayers are the expreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the heart, otherwiſe they are but empty.</p>
                  <p>There is another thing included too out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: they that pray as they ought, will <hi>indeavour to attaine what they pray for.</hi> It is not to bee beleeved, that a man prayeth for the peace of the Church, when hee doth that which is contrary to the peace of the Church, our indeavours therefore, muſt goe along with our prayers, or elſe it is no way ſutable.</p>
                  <p>Our indeavours in every kind, our <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> ſhould worke, we ſhould lay our heads together to work the welfare of the Church: <hi>our examples</hi> ſhould bee preſidents and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes to others to provoke them to good workes. Every one that hath any authority, <hi>his authority</hi> ſhould goe that way, for the ſetling, and furthering the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> elſe we doe but mocke. God in our prayers.</p>
                  <p>To adde one word concerning both the particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, wee ſhould <hi>pray our ſelves,</hi> and then <hi>ſtirre up others</hi> in the ſame way, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7995:13"/> performe the ſame duty.</p>
                  <p>And both of theſe muſt be done <hi>in the due manner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. Sincerely, not out of by-reſpects: To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend God and the Church, and to looke to a mans purſe, and to his owne private reſpects, is baſe and ſordid. 2. Wee ſhould doe this alſo earneſtly, and frequently, not as if wee cared not for it, but put our ſtrength to it, 3. Wee muſt doe it, conſtantly, not by fits, graſhopper-like, to skip up and fall downe againe preſently; but to hold a conſtant courſe of prayer.</p>
                  <p>To mention one thing more, <hi>Who is it,</hi> that are bound to doe all this (I expreſſed it in the point) <hi>Every Chriſtian,</hi> the <hi>true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> and <hi>every one</hi> that is ſuch muſt know it is a part of his duty.</p>
                  <p>Bee hee of what <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> ſoever h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e will, there may be a greater obligation upon ſome then others, but there is an obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in their places, it is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall piece of their ſervice, to pray for and to promote the peace, and welfare of the Church: and the <hi>people</hi> are not therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, for it belongs to them alſo.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their places, muſt be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perſons in their duty, and in the provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of others to it: and yet others are not thereby excuſed, but every member of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7995:14"/> Church as well as thoſe muſt pray.</p>
                  <p>Of what condition ſoever whither <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> or <hi>vnlearned,</hi> whether <hi>men</hi> or <hi>women,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but may bee ſould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers in this ſervico, women may worko here, their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections may be ſtrong, and every one hath a ſharo in it, it belongeth to all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> will adde no more for the explication of the point, and I will be alſo briefe in the prooft of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Scripture</hi> is very cleare, and doth lay many ſtrong obligations vpon us, for the performing of this duty, and we ſee many preſidents for it, of ſuch affections, that haue beene in the Saints of God, toward the Church of God, that they were carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the good of it, to the neglect of themſelues.</p>
                  <p>I will onely point you to ſome two, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> out of the hiſtoricall part of the Bible, both <hi>teſtimonies</hi> and <hi>examples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I. <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> it is a moſt incomparable example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi> 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itten, then ſuffer thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>iſh, and thy name to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by it. <hi>Moſes,</hi> was ſo farre tender of the good of the Church of God, that he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in a high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ll affection, rather to haue loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then God ſhould have loſt ſo much honour, as would haue bin by this meanes.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7995:14"/> In the 5. Chapter of <hi>Iudges,</hi> and the 23. verſe. The ſpirit of God, which is the ſpirit of bleſſing: yet thunders out curſes againſt thoſe that had no affection toward to Church. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> (ſaith the Angell of the Lord) yea, <hi>Curſe ye him bitterly, becauſe hee came not out to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> Not to bee ſenſible of the condition of the Church; and not to put in, with our beſt indeavours for it; bringeth a heavy curſe from the mouth of bleſſing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>II. And you may ſee, two excellent <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> of a man and a woman. In the 1 <hi>Sam. 4. 19. The wife of Phinehas,</hi> had the Church written in her heart more deepely then the ſonne of her wombe. Shee was newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of a ſon, but tooke no pleaſure in him, becauſe <hi>the Arke of God was taken.</hi> The other is of a man, that may plead as much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption as any, he was a ſouldier, and yet was a braue preſident in this caſe, in the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. Chapter, 11. verſe. <hi>Vriah,</hi> one of <hi>Davids</hi> worthies, would not goe home to his houſe; onely upon this appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, the deepe thought he had of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Church. <hi>My Lord Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (ſaith he to <hi>David) is in the field,</hi> and <hi>all Iſrael in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, and ſhall I goe home to take my pleaſure? As the Lord liveth I will not.</hi> All other plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures were nothing to him in reſpect of the welfare of the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7995:15"/>
                  <p>And in thoſe <hi>Doctrinall parts</hi> of the Old teſtament: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. 5. and 51. 18. and 53. 6. The Pſalmiſt in the middeſt of the heate of the proſecutions of his owne welfare, hath many out-lets, and breakings out of heart: <hi>O ſend ſalvation to Zion, build up the walls of Ieruſalem:</hi> Even when he was moſt buſie, to ſerue his owne turne, he cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the ſtate of the Church of God: <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber David in the midſt of all his afflictions.</hi> Minding not ſo much his owne particular, as the whole houſe of God, and therefore he ſaid, <hi>hee would not goe vp to his bedde, till he had found out a place for the Lord to dwell in.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So in <hi>Pſal. 102. 13. Haue mercy vpon Zion,</hi> for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>time to favour her is come.</hi> Such is the property of Gods ſervants, that the Church cannot lie in the duſt, but there is a tender pitty in the hearts of Gods people: in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 5. (an excellent place) <hi>If I forget thee, O Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning, if I preferre not Ieruſalem, before my chiefe ioy.</hi> And ſo in the prophecy of <hi>Eſay</hi> (that remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able place) in the 62. chap. <hi>for Zions ſake I will not hold my peace, I will not be ſilent, untill her righteouſneſſe bud forth,</hi> you that are the <hi>Lords remembrancers give him no reſt, vntill hee haue made Ieruſalem, the praiſe of the whole earth.</hi> It is an office acceptable with God; and all men that are of the Church, are of that office, to bee Gods remembrancers for his Church,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7995:15"/> to put him in mind of it. In the 22. of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> and the 12. verſe. When God did <hi>call for mourning,</hi> (in regard of the eſtate of the Church) and men ran to madnes, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, he was infinitely provoked by it. As I remember a common wealth, when the kingdome and ſtate was in great trouble a great many young ruffins being in a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne, were drinking: and they uſed to crowne there heads with ruſhes, which being done one of them lookt out at the window, which did ſo provoke the ſtate, that they tooke away his head for it. And that in <hi>Haggai:</hi> Is it time <hi>for you to dwell in ſeiled hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and my houſe not built?</hi> ſaith the Lord. It is not worth the while, to mind our owne houſes whilſt Gods houſe lyes in the Duſt.</p>
                  <p>To point at, 2. or 3. places, in the <hi>New Teſtament: Saint Pauls affection</hi> in this kind, that ſame in comparable affection, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 3. is not to be expreſſed, in which he para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelled <hi>Moſes,</hi> if not ſurpaſſed him: <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> deſire to be accurſed from Chriſt, for my brethrcus ſake.</hi> It noteth his infinite ſuperlatiue affection towards them. So in the 2 <hi>Cor. 11. 28. Phil. 1. 18. Col.</hi> 2. 5. You ſhall find how Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth, <hi>that all the care of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, lay upon him.</hi> As it was in the old law, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was never to enter into the holy of holieſt, but hee muſt haue his ornaments about him, all the twelue tribes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7995:16"/> to offer them up to God. So it was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, and ſhould be every miniſters, and every Chriſtians in their ſtation, but I forbeare.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall giue the <hi>grounds of the point,</hi> (in a word) from the ſeverall parcells, which we haue touched in the explication. Euery one of thoſe make a contribution, to raiſe the ſumme of a ſufficient reaſon, whether wee conſider.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The <hi>Nature of Ieruſalem,</hi> or</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Nature of Peace,</hi> or</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Nature of Prayer,</hi> or</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Nature of a Chriſtian.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>You ſhall find it ſtrongly demonſtrated in all theſe; That it is the duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Doe but</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, conſider the <hi>Nature of Ieruſalem,</hi> what <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is; the Church of God, and in it there is a double relation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If you looke vpward, the relation it hath to God, it is the <hi>houſe of God,</hi> it is <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> and can there bee a dearer relation to put a deeper ingagement vpon us, then to tender the ſpouſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or if you looke downeward, in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhee hath to us: <hi>Shee is the Mother of us all;</hi> all the Saints of God, are all the daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> all members of the Church, there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7995:16"/> is a naturall vnion, and comunion betweene them, and there ſhould be a fellow-feeling, of the good or ill, of the whole by every particular member.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Or if you conſider <hi>Peace,</hi> it is the <hi>ſumme of all bleſſings,</hi> it comprehends all bleſſings in the boſome of it. The ancients, were wont to paint peace with a horne of plenty.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Peace,</hi> it is the <hi>mother of all other proſperities,</hi> and bleſſing, arts, and ſciences, trades and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, flouriſh with peace: and all wither, if peace bee gone, warre blaſts all. And it is not onely the mother of all inferiour bleſſings: but</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is a very <hi>carefull and uſefull nurſe;</hi> to <hi>cheriſh religion,</hi> religion receiveth a great deale of advantage by peace, as in the <hi>Acts</hi> The <hi>Church had peace, and increaſed exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> As a Generall ſaid ſometimas, when one came to him for juſtice, what doeſt thou talke to mee of juſtice, (ſaith hee) I cannot heare the noiſe of Law and juſtice, for the ſounds of the drumms. There is no hearing of the Law of God, the Law of juſtice, when men haue their ſwords in their hands, there can be no roome for religion to grow up and thriue, if there bee not peace, to giue it a ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a ſetled place.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Or if you conſider the <hi>Nature of Prayer.</hi> What prayer is: (to mention onely the <hi>effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and <hi>neceſsity</hi> of it) I. It is the moſt <hi>effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7995:17"/> engine:</hi> the ſumme of all policies, for a Chriſtian to worke by, for Peace. Is it not <hi>God that ruleth all the world,</hi> and hath all hearts in his hands? he can make the very ſtones to be at peace with a man, he ſoders men toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Peace and warre depends upon him: and <hi>prayer rules God,</hi> he ſuffreth himſelfe to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by <hi>Prayer,</hi> Let me alone ſaith God: by prayer a Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etcheth all from God, what is in Gods power, is a Chriſtians by prayer: Yea there is ſuch an efficacy in it, that all the pollicies, of all the men in the world is nothing to Prayer, becauſe God is abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all, and can blaſt all.</p>
                  <p>II. It is <hi>of great neceſsity</hi> alſo; God will not beſtow bleſſings, but when a people will <hi>ſeeke him,</hi> and <hi>ſue to him</hi> for them, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is becauſe he ſhall haue <hi>little honour by it:</hi> if it came without our ſeeking it from God, we ſhould aſcribe it to ſome other way: God ſhould have no honour by it, but when it commeth begged by prayer, it appeareth to be the worke of God, and God hath the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it. So that hee doth not beſtow ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily bleſſings upon any, but at the requeſt of his people, where hee hath a people.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Or, Laſtly, If you conſider the <hi>nature of a Chriſtian,</hi> take him in relation to all theſe three former: or take him in another relation we ſhall adde. A godly man, it is the moſt proper worke for him, that can be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7995:17"/> imagined, he cannot bee excuſed of it.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. He is a <hi>Sonne of Ieruſalem,</hi> it becommeth him (at leaſt) to pray hard for his mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is an vnnaturall child, that will not open his mouth to ſaue miſcheife from his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As the Son of <hi>Craſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> that never ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before, the dumbe child through vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of tender affection, ſeeing one goe about to kill his father, cryed ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, O man wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou kill <hi>Craſus?</hi> it opened the dumbe mans mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that could not ſpeake before, to plead for his father in a caſe of danger. So ſhould it be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us for our Mother <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. Every child of God, is as a ſon of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> ſo a <hi>ſonne of Peace,</hi> we are the ſonnes of the <hi>God of peace;</hi> and ſonnes of the <hi>Goſpell of peace,</hi> and have all the ingagements of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> is a <hi>ſpirit of Peace:</hi> the ſpirit of the Dove ſhall reſt upon the ſpirit of the ſonnes of God, they are the ſonnes of Peace.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>He is the ſonne of Prayer,</hi> it ſhould be the very Element (ſaith <hi>Nazia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>)</hi> in which wee draw our breath, to run towards God, and towards Heaven, in the way of <hi>Prayer.</hi> So that a Chriſtian, that is the Sonne of God the Sonne of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Sonne of peace, and the Son of prayer: by all theſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tyes, is bound to pray for the peace of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> And ſo much the more, becauſe he is <hi>inabled;</hi> when others cannot; he hath <hi>abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and power, as he is the <hi>Sonne:</hi> it is in his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7995:18"/> hand, and he is able to be ſenſible of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and to pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which others cannot.</p>
                  <p>There bee 3. things in the generall, that I deſire to commend unto you, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this point by way of applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſet it home vpon your conſciences, for the performance of this duty.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we have here a <hi>cleare conviction,</hi> and <note place="margin">I.</note> 
                     <hi>reproofe</hi> of thoſe that <hi>doe the clean contrary,</hi> that doe not obſerue this, but fall ſhort of this duty, and doe not carry themſelves like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. There be 3. ſorts of men, (ſaith <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca)</hi> thoſe <hi>that doe evill;</hi> thoſe that doe <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> but <hi>by things;</hi> and thoſe that doe <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</hi> I might ſpeake of them in this forme: but I ſhall comprehend under this notion thoſe which doe <hi>contrary to this duty.</hi> They therefore eſpecially are to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that doe contrary. If this be the duty of all Chriſtians to pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> then how are they very Antipodes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtians, in a direct oppoſition unto them, that are not for <hi>Jeruſalem, but for Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. If there bee any Ieſuiticall ſpirit, that would build <hi>Rome,</hi> with the revenge of the ruines of <hi>England,</hi> as the firſt was built, this is cleane oppoſite to the text: if any one be not for <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> but for <hi>Babel,</hi> they are cleane contrary.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:7995:18"/>2. Againe if there be any Schiſmaticall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that are not <hi>for peace</hi> and proſperity: but for the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and deſtruction:</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> that trouble cities and trouble ſtates. <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er-</hi>like that cannot liue but in the <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ion,</hi> and make diſturbances. Like a ſimple man that cares not to ſet the houſe on fire, to roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. Such wicked ſpirits as are <hi>not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> had rather ſow diſcord and make breaches, to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>are and devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, one another in the Church of God, rather then ſtudy the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and concord of the Church: theſe are cleane contrary.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Againe they that are <hi>not for Ieruſalem, nor for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e leaſt of all for prayer:</hi> If it be the duty of all Chriſtians, to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to Heaven</hi> to helpe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the welfare of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Then what are they? and how unlike unto Chriſtians, that doe nothing but <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſalem?</hi> and <hi>goe</hi> to <hi>Hell</hi> by di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> throw, the Church of God, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and ſet up <hi>Babel,</hi> and a confuſed A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall end in this, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the day, of, Ieruſalem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> to the ground.</hi> God will have ſuch ſpirits in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:7995:19"/> godly man, hath theſe two advantages: The prayers of the godly: and the curſes of the wicked, and both of them to be bleſſings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, wee may every one of us make <note place="margin">II.</note> this a <hi>touch ſtone to try our ſelues,</hi> of what tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and mould we are: wee pretend all to Chriſtianity; wee doe not doubt, but that we are members of the Church of God, and of Chriſt; and wee hope to haue portion in both. To know whether this bee true, we may try it by <hi>our affection</hi> to the Church of God. How doth our hearts worke towards the Church? are our hearts <hi>ſoft?</hi> and doe they <hi>melt within us?</hi> and doe our hearts worke towards the repairing of the breaches of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſalem?</hi> This will giue a good teſtimony what we are, if it bee not thus, it is plaine we are not true genuine members, but wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den members of the Church: the liuing mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that receiue true nouriſhment from the head, have a fellow feeling, of the mll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry of the Church, but if wee be but as wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den legges, we ſhall bee cut off, and it is a ſigne weare but ſuch, if we haue no affection to it.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which is the principall: <note place="margin">III.</note> that what ouer we haue done hitherto, yet now, to take this as our duty, to carry the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> our bolom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the good, and peace of the Church of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7995:19"/> God, that God would <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſerue vs</hi> in peace that haue it, and that God would <hi>viſit in mercy,</hi> thoſe that haue had the ſword drunken in there blood a long time, wee ſhould make this a part of our prayer unto God. Many things ſhould haue beene ſaid here: but to omit all other things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If wee would pray for the Church of God, as wee ought, we muſt pray in <hi>Faith,</hi> beleeue Gods word, and the promiſes God hath made to his Church. Spread his book before him, and ſay: Lord, thou haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to doe good to thy Church, and that thou wouldſt confound the beaſt, and the Dragon, the appointed time ſeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to come now, thus pray to God, and preſſe him with his promiſes, and pray in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, as we muſt pray in faith: ſo pray in <hi>ſincere charity,</hi> in a true genuine loue to the Church of God, otherwiſe it will not bee worth the while.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Againe, <hi>Pray in repent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t up pure hands to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if thou art diligent in prayer, and negligent in thy life, and converſation, conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>g and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ing thy ſelfe with the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the world, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in it as any body, and thinkeſt to come off, becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n remembreſt the Church of God, thou art deceived. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thinke, God will heare thy prayers, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> commands: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>s you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:7995:20"/> your ſelues, from the vanities of this world, and you will not heare him, and doe you thinke he will heare you?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Pray with <hi>inſtancy and earneſtnes of ſpirit:</hi> a fearefull begger, teacheth how to giue a deniall. God loveth a kind of violence, to daſh our prayers againſt heaven, againſt the throne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> grace with a holy violence and zeale of ſpirit, which will prevaile much with God. The Iewes haue an old ſaying, which may have a good application. Since the deſtruction of the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the doore of prayers hath beene ſhut, God would not heare the people of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but yet the doore of teares is not ſhut, though God ſeemeth to ſtoppe againſt the doore of prayers, yet not againſt teares: if our <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers breake forth into teares,</hi> God will regard them. As I haue ſometimes obſerved of <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> that was wont to give certaine ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,but it was hard to make him ſpeake, and deliver them, but he would turne himſelfe, into ſeverall ſhapes and formes, yet if they would hold out, and preſſe him hard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, into whatſoever forme or ſhape he appeared, they were ſure to haue ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry oracles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So, God giveth not bleſſings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will wraſtle them out: and contend and ſtriue with God for them, by an earneſt and a ſervent ſpirit, And (as <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>llian</hi> ſaith) make <hi>prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> with faſting, which ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7995:20"/> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>arved with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rmalities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If God ſhould come and threaten to turne all upſide-downe; if wee make prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at with faſting, with ſervency of ſpirit, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and vigour of zeale, God would bee over-ruled by his ſervants: and I know nothing in the world, would be a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pledge of mercy, then if we could ſee the ſpirit of prayer among Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, <hi>Pray conſtantly.</hi> God may ſeeme to hide himſelfe, and not regard the prayers of his ſervants, but wee muſt not give over preſently, we muſt hold out and waite upon him. A nobleman you will waite upon, if you have any ſuite vnto him, and you will be glad if he giue you an anſwere at laſt, and ſhall wee thinke much to waite upon the doores of God, to giue the great Lord of Heaven, and earth a little attendance? this is but to ſerue our owne turne, if we doe not waite. We muſt waite, if God ſaith, as hee did to <hi>Moſes, Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> why trouble you mee? we muſt reſolve with <hi>Iacob</hi> not to <hi>let God goe till he bleſſe vs,</hi> this holy violence is good, if modeſt and conſtant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For <hi>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to helpe</hi> every one of vs, to a ſerious performance of this duty. In a word <hi>lay aſide our carnall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>rity,</hi> and <hi>lay things to heart:</hi> obſerue the eſtate of the Church of God, and lay it to heart, or elſe we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doe it, the ſaying is that which the eye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7995:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:7995:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:7995:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:7995:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:7995:23"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:7995:23"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:7995:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7995:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:7995:25"/> ſees not the heart rues not, if wee mind not theſe things, &amp; thinke not vpon them, if they doe not make an impreſſion into our hearts, we ſhall never faithfully make our expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto God. <hi>Take heed of the world,</hi> leaſt it doe with us, as the Ivy with the oake, which twiſts about it and hinders it from thriving. So the <hi>world</hi> twiſts about many a godly man, and Chriſtianity dies within him: take heed we be not too buſie with worldly affairs, that theychoak not all thoughts of better matters. There is a ſtory of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> the King asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had not obſerved the Eclipſes: No, (ſaith he) I have ſo much to doe upon earth, that I have no leiſure to looke up to heaven, A great many men have ſo much to doe upon earth, that they have no leiſure to thinke of heaven, or any thing belonging to the Church of God, they have ſo much to doe in the puzzleing affaires of this life, and have ſuch a roule of them hanging one upon another; that when one hath done, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother comes and woes them; that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have time to thinke of Gods Church; to lay to heart their duty in that kind. Many men while heaven, and earth, are on fire about their eares; and the Church of God in ruine, and themſelues in danger, yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are in the duſt, minding nothing but earth. As <hi>Archimides,</hi> the great Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7995:25"/> when the city was beſieged, himſelf did more by his curious art, to hinder the taking of it, then all the reſt of the city could doe to defend it, and the Generall of the enemy, gave a ſpeciall charge to preſerue <hi>Archimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi> Now the city being able to reſiſt no longer was taken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Archimides,</hi> hearing nothing all this while; the ſouldiers broke into the houſe where he was, yet he takes no notice: nay they broke into the ſtudy where he was: and the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſeeing him ſo buſie, drawing his lines in the duſt, not once mooving, nor taking any notice of them, one of them ſeeing him not regard them, out of a ſcornefull nature thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him diſregarded drew his ſword, and run him through, and killed him, whoſe death the Generall of the enemy greatly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. Let us not bury our ſelves in the duſt of worldly thoughts, and ſuffer the Churches to periſh, but let us ſhake off this duſt from us, and mind our duty in regard of the Church of God, and contend with God for the welfare of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For a few <hi>Motiues,</hi> beſides what I haue ſaid concerning <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> and the <hi>nature of a Chriſtian:</hi> and <hi>the nature of Prayer:</hi> It is that which <hi>God exacts at our hands:</hi> It is of that nature that it <hi>hath beene the practiſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and we ſhould not bee like them, but ſhould degenerate from them if we doe it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7995:26"/> not. It is that which <hi>becomes every one:</hi> and and it is the <hi>injunction of the Church,</hi> there is none that are baptized, but they are bound by their ſureties, to be taught the creed, and the Lords Prayer, and the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and they doe not love their creed, that wil not offer vp their praiers for the Church: They that are of the ſame faith, ſhould breath out the ſame breath of prayer, and they doe not keepe the ten Commandements that doe not ſay the Lords Prayer, that doe not offer vp their prayers for the Church of God: were wee of the ſame faith, and heart with the Church of God, our affections, could not poſſibly, but breake out that way.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve the motive in the Text, <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let no man flatter himſelfe, they that <hi>pray not</hi> for the Church of God, <hi>love not</hi> the Church of God. Let them proſper that love thee, that is, that pray for thee, the one is the counter-pane of the other: if we doe not love it we will not pray for it, and if we do not pray for it we doe not love it. Yea if we pray not for the Church, <hi>wee looſe our ſhare in the prayers of the Church,</hi> you will ſay that man hath a great eſtate that hath a part in every ſhip at ſea, and yet to have an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in all the prayers that are made to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are better then all the world: all the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7995:26"/> Churches praiers are for all the living mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, the bleſſings will be to them, for a man to have a venture in every ſhip of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of all the churches throughout the world, I would not (for my part) leaue my ſhare in it, for all the world, and that man hath no ſhare in it, that will not afford a prayer for the Church, <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee:</hi> Certainly, they ſhall proſper, they that doe love the Church, it ſhall goe well with them, and they ſhall proſper, and if they doe not, they ſhall not proſper. As <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> ſaid to <hi>Heſter,</hi> if thou doe not helpe, thou ſhalt periſh, but the Church of God ſhall have deliverance. So the Church of God, ſhall in the end proſper, but they that pray not for the Church of God, ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but periſh.</p>
                  <p>In a word the cauſe is <hi>great,</hi> and we have <hi>great propriety in it,</hi> and it concernes us neerely, though we bee remote in place, and the ſea part them and us.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>communion of the good;</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion <hi>of the evill</hi> of the Church, redounds to every particular member. And the <hi>times are ſuch,</hi> that a man would thinke they are times of prayer. Their enemies are as <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> as ever; and not onely ſo, but <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> and the Church of God all <hi>Millitant,</hi> in their warfare againſt their enemies; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour every way to their enemies; both
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7995:27"/> in <hi>armes,</hi> and <hi>counſell,</hi> their minds are not ſo ſodered together: breaches are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them which makes way for there ruine, and I know not what can ballance this but onely prayer. <hi>Joſhua</hi> though he bee the weakeſt; yet if <hi>Moſes</hi> be a praying in the Mount, he may prevaile. There is nothing can counterpoize the odds that is betweene the Church of God, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of it: nothing can make the ballance euen, and caſt the ſcale to the Church, but Prayer. And ſo much the more, becauſe <hi>God ſeemes to bee aſleepe</hi> in all their ſtormes, we ſhould ſay therefore, as they to <hi>Jonah, Ariſe and pray,</hi> wee ſhould goe and awaken every Chriſtian, to Prayer: that ſo wee may awaken God that ſeemes to ſleepe, and neglect, and let his Churches bee plunged in miſery.</p>
                  <p>Againe we may bee invited with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the <hi>iſſue of it:</hi> the ſhip of the Church may bee ſtill toſſed and tumbled, but becauſe Chriſt is in it, it can never periſh. The <hi>Romans</hi> loſt many a battell, and yet were conquerours in all their Warres. So it is with the Church of God: they have and may looſe many a battell, but in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion the Church will conquer, vnleſſe man could wraſtle with God, and beat him out of heaven, they ſhall never overcome his Church, or his truth-upon earth. Now
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7995:27"/> hee is a madde man, that will ſide with a badde cauſe, when hee is ſure the good cauſe will prevaile.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, to cloſe all, doe but conſider ſome <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> in the bowels of the <hi>nature of prayer,</hi> to invite us to it.</p>
                  <p>It is almoſt, <hi>the onely thing left</hi> that we can doe for them, when we ſee them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed round about with dangers, and there is no way to make an eſcape: Let us doe as <hi>Dedalus,</hi> that when he could not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape by a way upon earth, went by a way of Heaven. Let us goe by the way of heaven, and that is by prayer, that is the onely way that is left, and it is ſo <hi>eaſie a thing,</hi> and of <hi>ſo little coſt,</hi> that no man ſhould ſticke at it, to give a ſubſidie of prayers and ſighes this way. Yea every man ſhould doe this in his private cloſet and family; Pray that God would looke upon his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to reſtore peace where it is not, and to eſtabliſh it where it is, this is of ſo eaſie a coſt, mee-thinkes no man ſhould ſticke at it. As a ſtory hath it, there were a great many bookes of the Sybills, brought by a man to a King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and hee prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them to the King, at ſuch a rate, at a very great price, and the King would not give it: then the man burnt the one halfe of his bookes, and asked double the price that he did for the whole, the King refuſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7995:28"/> and he did the like with halfe of them, and doubled the price of all again, and then the King conſidering the value of them gave him the price. I am afraid, if wee forbeare to bid prayers for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> the time may come wee may be content to bid blood, and our eſtates, and yet not doe them one halfe quarrel ſo much good as we may now by prayer.</p>
                  <p>Againe, conſider what a <hi>ſoule blot it will bee,</hi> and what a brand it will ſet vpon vs, if we be defectiue in this kind. It is a <hi>perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> thing to betray the Church, and will leaue a great ſtaine, and a ſhame vpon us for ever. It is high time to pray, and therefore in my apprehenſion, you ſhould thinke it <hi>high treaſon,</hi> not to pray, he is a deſperate, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traytou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the ſtate of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that is not a daily and devout <hi>Oratour</hi> for the peace and welfare of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and it will <hi>leaue ſuch a ſlaine</hi> and <hi>ignomony</hi> behind, that will not eaſily be recompenced. It is an obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one that wrote the Hiſtory of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> relating what worthy acts many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had done: the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> did this valiant act, the <hi>Athenians</hi> did other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acts, and many other countries other worthy acts, and when it was demanded of him what his owne country-men of <hi>Cumin</hi> had done? he had nothing to ſay of them, but that they had done juſt nothing.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7995:28"/>
                  <p>Conſider, that if when wee have heard that others have done ſo much for the Church: and that in the Story it ſhould bee ſaid, wee have done juſt nothing, wee have not ſo much as prayed throughly for them; what a ſtaine would this bee: it will bee as great a ſtaine, and brand to vs, and as little honour to be regiſtred in Stories if wee ſhould doe nothing in this kind as it is for <hi>Pilate</hi> to have his name written in the Creed.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:29"/>
                  <p>A SERMON <hi>VPON</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> JOHN STOUGHTON, Doctor in Divinity, late of <hi>Alderman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quanto major Honor datur, Tanto majus Periculum comparatur.</hi> Auguſt. Ser. 62. <hi>ad frat. in Eremo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Dawſon,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop, at the three golden Lions in <hi>Cornehill</hi> neere the Royall Exchange, 1640.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="analysis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:30"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:30"/>
                  <head>A Methodicall <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the principall things treated of in this Sermon, as it was perfected by the <hi>Author.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <head>1 SAM. 2. 30.</head>
                     <item>1. <hi>Jntroduction.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Context. The Judiciall Proceſſe of God againſt</hi> Eli,
<list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>The ſinne of</hi> Eli.
<list>
                                       <item>1 <hi>Of his Sonnes,</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <hi>Of himſelfe.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The ſentence of God againſt him: wherein</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Gods gracious exaltation of him,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>His juſt Degradation.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Text. Wherein obſerve,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Elies <hi>Pattent for Honour,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The Revocation of that Pattent</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 <hi>The reaſon of that Revocation.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 Elies <hi>Sinne,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Gods Iuſtice.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Obſervations of his Honour;</hi> 1. <hi>From</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>The ſeverall poſtures of it:</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>The toppe of Honour,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>The fall of Honour,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>The riſe of Honour,</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The Charactaristicall nature of it.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The State of Honour,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Rule of Honour.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Tractation.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Doct. <hi>The ſervice of God in the Miniſterie is a very honourable function.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Explication.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>What Miniſtry,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Legall,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Evangelicall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>How is it honourable:</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7995:31"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>In reſpect of the qualitie of it there is a Double</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Honour,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Civill,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Spirituall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Title to it from the</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Office.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Probation.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>: <hi>by Scripture.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>: <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All things in their function are honourable.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>They ſerve an Honourable Lord, the King of Heaven.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>They ſerve in an Honourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>mployment,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>As Gods Legats,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>As Chriſts Colleagues.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 <hi>Their gifts are Honourable</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Of Knowledge,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Of Eloquence,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>Of Conſcience.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>4 <hi>Their reward is Honourable.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Application.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Conſolation.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Inſtruction.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Of the Church,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Of the Magiſtrates,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>Of Miniſters,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>Of Candidates,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>5 <hi>Of the People.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>1 <hi>The Peoples Duty:</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Acknowledge their Honour,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Carry themſelves accordingly.</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1 <hi>Jn a due reſpect,</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <hi>Jn a noble Stipend,</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>3 <hi>Jn a facile obedience.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Motives.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Equity of the Duty,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Greatneſſe of the Sinne</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1 <hi>Againſt God,</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <hi>Againſt themſelues</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>Sharpnes of the puniſhment.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:7995:31"/>
                  <head>A SERMON VPON</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>1 SAM. 2. 30.</bibl>
                     <q>Wherefore the Lord God of Iſraell ſaith, I ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father ſhould walke before me for ever: but now the Lord ſaith, bee it farre from me: for them that honour me, J will honour, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides other things, this is one maine part of the Chapter: The Iudiciall proceſſe of God againſt <hi>Eli,</hi> in which wee may obſerue theſe two ſteps, or degrees. Firſt, wee have the <hi>ſinne of Eli againſt God.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we have the <hi>ſentence of God againſt Eli.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I. The ſinne of <hi>Eli</hi> againſt God, which was partly, <hi>the ſinne of his ſonnes,</hi> in the twelfth <note place="margin">1. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Eli</hi>
                     </note> verſe. And partly <hi>his owne perſonall ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His ſonnes:</hi> of them is noted, the looſeneſſe of their lives in the office of the Prieſthood, in <note place="margin">1 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> many particulars.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:7995:32"/>
                  <p>For <hi>Elies ſinne in his owne perſon;</hi> is noted the looſenes of his diſcipline, that he carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">2 <hi>Ipſius.</hi>
                     </note> too remiſſely, and indulgently towards his ſonnes, in caſe of their ſinning, and then</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as we have the ſinne of <hi>Eli</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sententia Dei.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>God:</hi> So, vpon that, the ſentence of God <hi>againſt Eli,</hi> wherein we may obſerve 2. diſtinct things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gods gracious exaltation of him:</hi> ver. 27. which <note place="margin">1. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                              <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> God mentions by way of introduction, evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the equity of his proceedings againſt <hi>Eli:</hi> he doth it by a commemoration, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of all the mercy, which hee had beſtowed upon him, and upon his family: that he had pickt him out from among the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and advanced him to the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Prieſthood. And this is brought in as an aggravation of his ſinne. <hi>I ſaid</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father ſhould walke before mee for ever:</hi> how durſt thou then doe ſuch a thing as to kicke at my ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and at my offering, which I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in my habitation, and honoureſt thy ſons aboue me.</p>
                  <p>Now this being cleare, and the equity, and juſtice of the ſentence being evinced, wee have</p>
                  <p>Secondly, (in the words of the Text) <hi>his juſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Iuſta De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradatio.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>degradation, and the ſeverity of the ſentence,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may obſerve (to give briefly the ſumme of it) theſe 3. things.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:7995:32"/>
                  <p>In the beginning of the verſe, you have a pattent or graunt of honour to <hi>Eli,</hi> and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: <note place="margin">1. <hi>Conceſſio Honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> I ſaid <hi>thou and thy fathers houſe ſhould walke before me for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, we have the revocation of that graunt but now thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Farre bee</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Revocatio Conceſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>it from me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we have <hi>the reaſon of that revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                              <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> why his pattent and graunt of honour was revoked and called in: wherein there is</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jmplyed, in the ſinne of Eli,</hi> his provoking God <note place="margin">1. <hi>Culpa Eli.</hi>
                     </note> by deſpiſing and <hi>not honouring of him,</hi> in the place of honour that God had ſet him in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Directly expreſt,</hi> the <hi>Iuſtice of God</hi> and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines <note place="margin">2. <hi>Iuſtitia Dei.</hi>
                     </note> of his nature, which would not ſuffer him to winke at ſuch exorbitancies: it is incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with his nature, to beare with ſuch inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: he ſhould deny his nature, if he did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it; in the laſt words; <hi>thoſe that honour mee I will honour, but thoſe that deſpiſe mee ſhall bee lightly eſteemed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before I enter into the conſideration of the words read, I ſhall propound but one obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the hiſtory, which though perhaps it may ſeeme ſomething curious, yet I know it may be exceeding profitable. In the main of the ſtory, we may, both in regard of every Perſon and every family, and every State, and every Church, ſee a mirrom of the courſe of honour, and the <hi>ſleppes by which it doth decline.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:7995:33"/>
                  <p>I onely note thus much out of this ſtory, in one thing.</p>
                  <p>Wee have here three generations recorded to us: <hi>Eli, Phinchas,</hi> and <hi>Ichabod. Eli,</hi> he begets <hi>Phinchas,</hi> and <hi>Phinchas</hi> he begets <hi>Ichabod.</hi> Now in <hi>Eli</hi> God taxeth <hi>remiſſenſſe,</hi> want of zeale: in <hi>Phinchas</hi> he taxeth <hi>prophaneneſſe,</hi> want of conſcience: and <hi>Ichabod,</hi> (his very name boades no other.) <hi>The glory is departed from Iſrael.</hi> The note then is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let but Zeale in a perſon, in a Family, in a ſtate or Church; once degenerate to luke-warmeneſſe, and then luke-warmeneſſe will ſoone beget prophanenes, and prophaneneſſe will not be long before it doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate, and bring us to ruine, that will bring in</hi> Ichabod, <hi>the glory is departed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Want of zeale is the firſt ſtep, from whence there is but one diſcent to ruine. This being thus briefly premiſed, I ſhall now fall to the words of the Text.</p>
                  <p>And the text may ſeeme to bee a Charter of the Clergy, or a Kalender for all manner of dignity: or it is a perpetuall prognoſtication of the courſe of honour, though calculated for the Meridian of the high Prieſthood, yet ſuch as may ſerve (as thoſe men vſe to ſpeake) for the generall latitude of all eminency, and may concerne all.</p>
                  <p>There bee but theſe 5. things: (though there might be many more) which I will take notice of, in the whole verſe. We have.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:7995:33"/>
                     <item>
                        <label>The</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Place</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Fall</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>State</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>of honour.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. <hi>Riſe</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>5. <hi>Rule</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And ſo many things the words imply, and in ſhort, you may eaſily have them at your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ends.</p>
                  <p>In the three former, we have the <hi>ſeverall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures</hi> of honour and</p>
                  <p>In the two latter, wee have the <hi>characteriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call nature</hi> of honour.</p>
                  <p>In the three former, the ſeverall poſtures of honour: there is</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Honour <hi>Culmenant,</hi> in the <hi>dignity</hi> of the <hi>high-prieſthood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Honour <hi>Occident,</hi> in the fall <hi>and declining</hi> of it.</item>
                     <item>3. Honour <hi>Orient,</hi> in the <hi>riſe of it,</hi> which is from God. There is likewiſe</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The <hi>Characteriſticall nature of</hi> honour.</p>
                  <p>The whole <hi>ſpheare</hi> or the whole globe of honour, hangs very tickle, and it is a very hard thing, to mannage honour well.</p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Horizon,</hi> that bounds both the Hemiſpheares, is the laſt thing that I propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Rule, by which the juſtice of God doth weigh (as it were) in the ballance all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and that by which it either riſes up, or falls, and declines. One the one ſide, <hi>Grace ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:7995:34"/> and perpetuates honour, and on the other ſide, <hi>Sinne degrades,</hi> and evacuates ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. <note place="margin">Obſervatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Honoris.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that according to theſe 5. there will bee but 5. points I ſhall take notice of out of theſe words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the ſervice of God in the Miniſtery, is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Doct. Titulu. Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ſervice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>(For I ſhall propound it thus rather in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality, then particularly confine it to the high Prieſt-hood, which was the ſervice of thoſe times) I ſay the ſervice <hi>of God in the Miniſtery</hi> (how ever men eſteem of that ranke and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,) <hi>is an honourable ſervice.</hi> I ſaid (ſaith God) thou ſhouldeſt walke before mee: it is a walking before God. The ſcripture makes a <hi>Periphraſis</hi> of the <hi>dignity</hi> of Kings; <hi>walking in and out before their people.</hi> Kings they walke before their people, and miniſters they walke before God. The miniſtery, and ſervice of God in it, is an honourable ſervice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is no eminency but is ſubject to the Epilepſy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. Status mobilis</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>there is no honour but may have the falling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no pattent God grants of perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity to any man. As the Lawyer ſpeaks: it is not <hi>durante vita,</hi> but <hi>durante bene placito.</hi> God grants no man a pattent for honour during his life, but during his owne good pleaſure, it is not as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7995:34"/> ſome men haue it, <hi>quoad vixeret,</hi> but <hi>quoad ſic geſſeret,</hi> ſo long as as a man lives, but ſo long as a man carries himſelfe, toward God as hee ought to doe. There is no honour but is ſubiect to mutability, it is an vnſtable, and ſlippery place: The very ſtate of honour, even when it is in the very flower, and height, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it, yet then it is a very ſlippery place.</p>
                  <p>In the next place;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is a very hard, and difficult thing, to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3 <hi>Doct. Munus diffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>honour without danger.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then again (though I know that it might have bin martialled otherwiſe, and preferred a little higher; but yet here it is more proper for my ſcope) there will bee another part which is:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All honour is not from the earth, but from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">4. <hi>Doct. Ortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtis</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>from God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is God that raiſeth to honour and he that ruines: it is he that puls downe, it is God that rules all, all is from him, the diſpoſing of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is in the hand of God: as in Heraldry, it is a received maxime, that the King is the fountaine of honour, it is moſt true here; the King of heaven is the fountaine of honour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The equitable rule of Juſtice, by which God doth diſpence, or deny honour is according as men doe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">5. <hi>Doct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Equa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ile.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>honour or deſpiſe God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:7995:35"/>
                  <p>And that is expreſt in the laſt words, <hi>for them that honour mee I will honour, and they that deſpiſe mee ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the firſt Point. <hi>That the ſervice of God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Doct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                              <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>in the Miniſtery,</hi> (howſoever the world account it contemptible, yet) <hi>it is a very honourable fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Briefly to open the point.</p>
                  <p>There are but two things, and that in a word <note place="margin">1. <hi>Expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>atio propoſit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> I ſhall ſpeake of.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>What ſervice</hi> and <hi>what miniſtery</hi> is honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. How and in what reſpect it is honourable.</p>
                  <p>I. <hi>What ſervice,</hi> and what miniſtery is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Quod</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In a word, that ſervice is honourable, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a man is in imediate attendance vpon God, and that belongs to his ſpeciall family as it were (as Miniſters doe) the ſervice of thoſe is honourable.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, whether it bee <hi>legall:</hi> in thoſe that <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> lived under the ſtate of the law, it was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable place and ſervice then, to belong to God, even in the legall ſervices, and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Temple. Therefore in the</p>
                  <p>Second place, (for the Apoſtle ſo reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth) if the <hi>ſervices,</hi> and employments that <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> were <hi>legall</hi> vnder the law were honourable, much more thoſe ſervices, that are <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> under the Goſpell. There being ſo many things that doe much advance, and nothing that doth impure that honour; there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7995:35"/> to thinke that it ſhould ſuffer diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, in the ſtate of the Goſpell: if the legall ſervice were ſo honourable, then is the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall ſervice in the miniſtery, for that hath not loſt but rather gained in point of nour, but</p>
                  <p>Secondly, How muſt it bee underſtood? <hi>in what ſence,</hi> and in what reſpect, is this ſervice <note place="margin">1. <hi>Quomodo.</hi>
                     </note> of God honourable? in one word there may bee:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A double honour, and </p>
                  <p>A <hi>double right</hi> to that honour. <note place="margin">2. <hi>Quoad</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>A double honour. A <hi>Civill honour,</hi> and a <hi>Spirituall Honour,</hi> and it is true, theſe can <note place="margin">1. <hi>Qualitatem: Duplex honor Civilis Spiritualis.</hi>
                     </note> hardly bee ſeparated among men, but the thing I ſpeake of, aimes, not at civill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that the ſervice of the miniſtery is honourable in civill reſpects: that there is a civill honour due to them, more or leſſe is plaine: for it is impoſſible that if there bee a ſpirituall honour due to any, but that men that underſtand themſelves ſhould make ſome expreſſion of it in ſome ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill way, but the ſpiritual honour is that which I aime at, now beſides this double honour, there is</p>
                  <p>A <hi>double right and title</hi> to this honour; any <note place="margin">2. <hi>Duplex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>na Officio</hi>
                     </note> perſon may be honourable: or, an office may bee honourable, honour may bee either in regard of the <hi>perſon,</hi> or in regard of the office it ſelfe.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7995:36"/> Some mens perſons are of that worth: as he ſaid ſometime, when others were ſtriving who ſhould ſit higheſt at the feaſt, place mee where you will, I will honour the place where my ſelfe ſits. Some men by their worth may obtaine, and command more honour then the eminency of the place doth afford. As a Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant being in the bottome of a well, though hee be in a very low place, yet he is a Giant, and a great man ſtill, and a dwarfe though hee bee upon high upon the top of a mountaine, yet he remaines a dwarfe ſtill. Perſonall reſpects may deſerve honour, may give a man title to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſo in that reſpect, their may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due to an inferiour office, but I meddle not now with perſonall honour that may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this or that Miniſter, in regard of his perſonall excellencie, but the thing that I aime at for the preſent is.</p>
                  <p>That the very <hi>office of the miniſtery is,</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>honourable:</hi> though their be not in a man perſonall Eminencies, that may command ſpeciall reſpect; yet if hee be in the place of the Miniſtery, there is an honour due to him in reſpect of his place, and in reſpect of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Not that I entend here to make a vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with honour; as ſome Papiſts have done, as one of them ſaid: If he ſhould meet with an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and a <hi>Prieſt</hi> together, he would firſt doe his duty to the Prieſt, and then afterward ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the Angell, but I am ſure in ſome reſpects
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7995:36"/> the office of the miniſtery, is not inferiour to the Angelicall office. I ſhall ſay no more for the opening of the point</p>
                  <p>For the proofe of it, in a word: I ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> be very ſparing, but I cannot altogether omit it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of all for the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of it that it is ſo, I <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſhall forbeare particular teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſuppoſing the thing to be plaine enough: Thoſe <hi>titles</hi> and many other things given to them, and thoſe many <hi>records</hi> in ſcripture may make it appeare clearely; that the ſervice of the miniſtery is an honourable ſervice, but I <note place="margin">Scriptura.</note> will give but a touch of ſome few things.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt beginnings of the world, and of mankind, the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and ſervice of God proportionable to thoſe times, did deſcend to the <hi>birth-right:</hi> the eldeſt, and moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the family, did ſucceed in the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: To omit the conceits of the ancient Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of thoſe times whoſe ſpeeches were <hi>Rex amicus rex idem hominum at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſacerdos,</hi> it was not ſtrange to have a man a Prieſt of the moſt high God, and a king of regions: but yet in ſcripture wee know that <hi>Melchiſedec, was King of Salem, and Prieſt of the moſt high God,</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward vnder the Law, though it pleaſed God to ſever theſe two: <hi>Ruben was the firſt borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his brethren,</hi> and ſo had the <hi>right of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> by nature: and ſo the Sacerdoticall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhould have reſted upon him: yet you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7995:37"/> know how God by his father <hi>Iacob</hi> (the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God directing him) tranſlated this, and divided it betweene two, the honour of the birthright was faſtned upon <hi>Levi. As Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ben loſt</hi> it for his <hi>ſinne,</hi> So <hi>Levi got</hi> it for his zeale, in excecuting the commands of God upon vile ſinners. God tooke it ſo well at his hand, that he gave him the Prieſthood for it, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther piece of the birthright, the other dignity, that was tranſlated from <hi>Ruben</hi> to <hi>Judah,</hi> ſo that became the royall tribe. Now it ſhewes that the office of the Prieſthood is a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable office. <hi>Levi</hi> attaining it by the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, being the <hi>eldeſt adopted ſonne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> there is many titles of dignity, and many intimations of the honour of this office. The <hi>Miniſters</hi> are the <hi>ſeaven golden Candleſticks,</hi> and the lights in thoſe Candleſticks; and not <hi>inferiour lights,</hi> for they are <hi>ſtars in the right hand of God,</hi> the <hi>Angels of the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>ground and reaſon</hi> of <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the point, why any man in reaſon cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide it, but muſt aſſent unto it; <hi>viz.</hi> that the office of the miniſters of God is very honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to omit perſonall reſpects though that might ſerve to convince baſe ſpirits, that have a baſe eſteeme of them, their education is inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, they are bred ingeniouſly, in all litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which all doe account, though not one of the liberall ſciences, yet one that is more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7995:37"/> honourable then all the reſt, and many other things that belong to that, as wiſedome, or eloquence, or vertue which will beautifie and adorne and make a man honourable, that hath no chinke, or gold, or purchaſe, or birth-right or blood, but I forbeare thoſe, onely whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever viewes, and conſiders well, ſhall find, that all things concerning Miniſters in their place are honouriſicable: It is <hi>the Lord</hi> whom they <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſerve, and he is honourable; <hi>the ſervice</hi> in which their Lord employes them, is <hi>great and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> their worke is great and their <hi>wages</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is great, and honourable, I will touch but a little theſethings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſerve a great Lord,</hi> and I pray, what <note place="margin">1 <hi>Domirus. Rex Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> makes the ſervants of Kings and Princes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, but the honour, and the greatneſſe of their Maſters? there is a reflection from their maſters that guilds over them, and makes them to bee in an honourable eſtate: and ſhall not the ſervants of the king of kings be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted honourable, that have immediate depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and attendance vpon him? it is the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a great Senator of <hi>Rome,</hi> hee would willingly (in the great concuſſions, that had ſcattered the whole common wealth) have recovered the liberty, that before they had, but ſeeing they were neceſſitated, and that they muſt needs lay downe their liberty and chuſe a Maſter, he ſaid he would chuſe <hi>Pompey,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe hee thought him to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7995:38"/> bee more noble, verttuous, and more ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, towards the ſtate of that common wealth and his reaſon was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and may not wee ſay more truely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>? to be a ſervant, and not to bee a mans own man is ſome diſhonour and diminution in it ſelfe, but that is ſuch a diminution, that no man can avoide, we muſt be all ſervants, there is no helpe for that: now this makes an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſervice, to ſerve an honourable Maſter; in that caſe, an honourable ſervice is more conſiderable, then abſolute freedome and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, for their maſter is the King of heaven, a meane ſervant belonging to the King, in any office about him, is more honourable, then many an honeſt freeman: the meaneſt of Gods ſervants, the Miniſters, is honourable. But</p>
                  <p>They are not onely ſervants of a great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <note place="margin">2. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> but <hi>ſervants in an honourable condition</hi> and imployment: their imployment under God, and in his ſervice is very honourable. To pitch upon two particulars, and omit all other things, wherein the honour of their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is preſented to vs:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They are employed as <hi>Gods Legates,</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They are imployed, as <hi>Chriſts Colleagues,</hi> and companions in that ſervice. </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They are imployed as <hi>Gods Legats,</hi> and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and that is no diſhonourable place; nay, it is by the law of nations counted an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſervice: To be an <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7995:38"/> the perſon of the king himſelfe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome of ſome kingdomes, though a man of inferiour ranke be imployed for the Kings ſervice that way, he doth obtain the title of honourable as long as hee lives, though he have no other dignity. Now as the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>we are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by vs, wee pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be reconciled to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But there may be a great deale of difference of Ambaſſadors, according to the nature of the Ambaſſage they are imployed in: there be ſome meane ambaſſages men may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e bee ſome other, that are of higher importance and concernement, that all men are not capable of. Now can there be a greater imployment and ambaſſy, from God to man, than thoſe arrands and buſineſſes which the Miniſters of God are imployed in? (To omit all other circumſtances) they are not imployed about petty and inferiour things, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout quarrels or brawles, or ſuch like things: or matters of commerce, or trade in generall, but they are employed about the Staple-trade and <hi>maine commerce betweene Heaven, and earth:</hi> they are Ambaſſadours in things of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concernement: not of things belonging to the body, but to <hi>the ſoule:</hi> and of things that belong to the ſoule, not in ſmall, and inferiour things, but ſuch things as concerne the <hi>very vitalls</hi> and <hi>higheſt excellencies of the ſoule,</hi> to bring
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7995:39"/> 
                     <hi>felicity,</hi> and <hi>eternity</hi> to the ſoule, to helpe and further men in the <hi>way to heaven;</hi> as it were reducing them to <hi>an affinity,</hi> to a contraction of a marriage with God himſelfe, and of all ſervices in the world, and of all Ambaſſages, thoſe that are imployed by Princes to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate their marriages, are accounted moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</p>
                  <p>And as their <hi>relation</hi> is honourable, they are <hi>Gods ſervants,</hi> and their <hi>imployment</hi> is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, they are <hi>Gods Ambaſſadours:</hi> So they are in this buſineſſe, not onely Legates of God: But</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Colleagues with Chriſt;</hi> in joynt commiſſion with Chriſt himſelfe. Now doe you thinke that the ſervice, which Chriſt himſelfe acted the part of, ſo long as hee was in the world was contemptible? <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe was the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> of God, for thoſe ſame ends, that his Miniſters are (though in a higher degree) hee did that which properly belonged to himſelfe <hi>as a Mediator,</hi> paying the price of our redemption, yet he did this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as hee was a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> to reduce and bring men vnto God, I ſay, it was the office of Chriſt in which he ſpent his time upon earth. Now to be joyned with Chriſt, to be his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, to be in joynt commiſſion with him, muſt needs bee honourable: nay the ſcripture expreſſeth ſomething to adorne them higher, for they are ſaid to <hi>bee fellow labourers with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7995:39"/> God,</hi> &amp; that in the <hi>greateſt worke,</hi> that is, in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of men,</hi> as it is the ſaying of the Father, the <hi>greateſt worke of the Divinity is,</hi> in <hi>taking care for our humanity,</hi> to ſave our ſoules, now that God would make his Miniſters <hi>fellow labourers</hi> with himſelfe, it is a very <hi>honourable conjunction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then <hi>gifts</hi> are <hi>honourable,</hi> whether they be <hi>gifts</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of <hi>knowledge, learning, eloquence,</hi> or <hi>conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, as their maſter they ſervers honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and then ſervice honourable, and gifts honourable: So their <hi>reward</hi> is alſo <hi>honourable.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> I cannot ſpeake of the <hi>reward they have here in their way,</hi> nor is it to be expected that they ſhould have great matters here, the leſſe they have here, the more remaines for them in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: the Papiſts have a conceit that beſides the <hi>crowne of glory,</hi> and immortallity, that ſhall be given to every faithfull Chriſtian, there is a <hi>Coronate alſo of glory,</hi> which ſhall give a luſtre to the former: and ſhall be given to 3. ſorts of perſons, to <hi>Martyrs,</hi> to <hi>Virgins,</hi> and to <hi>Doctors,</hi> and they give the reaſon, becauſe there is 3|grand-enemies, <hi>viz.</hi> the world, the fleſh, and the Devill: and theſe 3. ſorts of perſons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them. The <hi>Martyrs,</hi> they ſhall have a <hi>Crowne,</hi> becauſe they are imployed in the front of the battell againſt the <hi>world,</hi> they are ſet (as it were) at Cannons mouth, againſt all the oppoſitions of the world, and they make their ſtation good, and maintaine Gods cauſe, and bidde defiance to all the world, they defie the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7995:40"/> world, and dare it to doe them hurt.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>virgins,</hi> that live, and continue always ſo, they bidde defiance to the fleſh, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt have their crowne. And the <hi>Doctors</hi> alſo, they muſt have a crowne, becauſe they have the greateſt enemy to encounter with, and ſtand in the greateſt oppoſition, to bid defiance to the devill himſelfe, and all his policies, by which he doth ſeduce men: and they are moſt expoſed to perill, becauſe they are Gods particular inſtruments which God vſeth to reduce men from the jawes of the Devill, and therefore becauſe they goe away conquerors in this, there is a particular Coronet for them. I mention not this to juſtifie eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry notion in it, but ſure I am the reward of the Miniſters ſhall be a heavenly reward: It is true, there is but little preferment, or incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, nothing ſutable to the honour we have ſpoken of, that Miniſters have here. As you know Ambaſſadours have not preferment while they are abroad, but when they come home in their owne countrey their King will preferre them, and ſo God doth, he lets it till they come home, and then <hi>Thoſe that convert</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the ſunne in the firmament,</hi> ſhewing that there is a peculiar honour belongs to the Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>To come then to the Application of the <note place="margin">2. <hi>Applicatio.</hi>
                     </note> point,</p>
                  <p>1. This may be <hi>matter of comfort,</hi> to the <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>atio.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:7995:40"/> 
                     <hi>Miniſters</hi> of God, againſt thoſe that condemne their perſons and miniſtery; and this is matter of conſolation, to beare them up againſt all ſcornes, and indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that are put upon them in regard of their miniſtery. As the Poet reports a ſtory of a certaine rich man, that when hee went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, the people that met him, would curſe him, and call him <hi>bite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>igge,</hi> he being a very niggard, yet (ſaith hee) very wittily, <hi>Populus me ſibilat, at mihi met ipſe plaudo domi,</hi> When I come home to my counting houſe, and ſeeing the angells ſmiling vpon mee, I comfort my ſelfe againſt all thoſe ſcornefull ſpeeches. So may not the faithfull miniſters of Chriſt doe in the like caſe when the world ſcoffes at them? that when as it is ſaid unto them, as it was ſaid vnto <hi>Eliſha Come vp thou bald pate, Come up thou bald pate:</hi> may not they counterpoize this, when as they goe home and come into their cloſets and looke upon the <hi>charter,</hi> and the <hi>commiſsion</hi> that they have from God, that they have a commiſſion from the God of heaven, to be his ſervants, in choiſe imployments may not they ſay to themſelves, did not God appoint us to walke in this way? did hee not ſet us in this place and office? and he it is that ſaith, <hi>I will honour thee,</hi> it is enough that he ſaith <hi>I will doe it,</hi> he hath not promiſed that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callity of the world ſhall honour them, but that hee himſelfe will doe it, and <hi>laudar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7995:41"/> viro, ea demum eſt vera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aus. i. e.</hi> they ſhall receive honour from one, which is honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble indeed, and that is true honour. To paſſe the vſe of reproofe.</p>
                  <p>This point may be of good Vſe for inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to inſtruct all ſorts and conditions. <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, it may be a good <hi>Item</hi> to thoſe that ſhall ſit at the ſterne of the <hi>Church,</hi> to take care <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> whom they doe give admittance and way to in the entrance into the miniſtery. It is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable ſtory of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> the father of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great, that when he was advanced to honour, there were about him, <hi>many Pagans</hi> and many <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and he (to diſcover who were Chriſtians, and who were not) made an edict: that all thoſe that were Chriſtians, and would not worſhip the heathen Gods, ſhould immediately depart from the Court; upon this all the Pagans ſlockt about him, and many falſe hearted Chriſtians alſo preſented their ſervice to him, to whom he made this anſwer nay (ſaies he) <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f you will bee falſe to your God,</hi> I will never truſt <hi>you to bee a ſervant to me.</hi> It behooveth the governours of the Church to prevent this, that no vnworthy perſons be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the office of the miniſtery to bee a ſervant of God in ſo choiſe an imployment. It was <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſinne,</hi> that <hi>he made Prieſts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of the people,</hi> and it is a ſoule ſhame, and ſinne, that God ſhould be ſerved with baſe and vnworthy perſons, that ſuch ſhould goe for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7995:41"/> his Ambaſſadours, that caſt a diſgrace, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour vpon the office it ſelfe: the ſaying is of old, every blocke is not fit to build in Gods houſe, at leaſt to be a builder, a principall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to bee a Miniſter, and diſpencer of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpell. Therefore this may be a good Item to the Church, to take heed who they admit into this office. But humbly, by way of inſtruction, I ſhall need ſay but this:</p>
                  <p>There is two things required, to make any office warrantable, and authentike in this caſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 There muſt be an <hi>Externall Calling,</hi> and</p>
                  <p n="2">2 There muſt be an <hi>Internall Calling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Without the <hi>Externall Calling</hi> of the Church who can take vpon him, and vſurpe, ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as this is?</p>
                  <p>And without an <hi>internall calling,</hi> what right hath the Church to put any into ſuch an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable office? therefore it is the Churches part, to examine whether they whom they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into this office, have a commiſſion from God or no: and the ſeales of it muſt be.</p>
                  <p>Ability, and</p>
                  <p>Integrity.</p>
                  <p>Ability, for matter of Doctrine, and Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for matter of Converſation; and they that doe not bring with them their commiſſion from God, with theſe ſeales, ſhould not End admiſſion from the Church.</p>
                  <p>This may be a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to Magiſtrates</hi> that <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> have (though not the acting of any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7995:42"/> buſines, yet have) the over-looking of all, and are to have a care of the Church, that all things goe well with them, to <hi>fence and hedge</hi> about the Miniſters that every wilde beaſt may not tread them downe, that it may not be the cheapeſt thing in the world, to ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who is Gods Ambaſſadour, to ſuffer them to bee evilly dealt withall, and ſhamefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated: Shall any one? ſhall a player, have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quarter, then a Miniſter? this is a hard thing: it therefore concernes the Magiſtrates (if this be an honourable place) to fence it; that there may not be liberty to diſhonour it, by every one that pleaſeth.</p>
                  <p>It may be a <hi>good Item to all Miniſters,</hi> to <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the honour of their place, and not to ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh or evacuate it with their vnworthines, the place it ſelf is honorable, &amp; ſome men may caſt a luſtre, and honour upon the place, and ſome men may again defile it, and diſgrace it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to contempt and deriſion, as he ſaid of the learned Cardinall, he was a learned man, and for it was advanced to a Cardinallſhip, but when he came to that advancement, <hi>quo demum major eo melior,</hi> he did adorne the ſcarlet robe that hee wore with more then ſcarlet worth. Let every one labour to <hi>adorne</hi> the place, and advance the honour of the place by his worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and take heed hee doe not make the place vile, for his perſons ſake, but take notice of thoſe things, that makes the miniſtery truely
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7995:42"/> honourable, and indeavour after them. As la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for thoſe <hi>abilities,</hi> that are required, and neceſſary to ſuch a place: there ſhould be in men ſome competency that way: that they may not bee a ſhame to the place of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery. And labour to adorne the place with <hi>diligence, and fidelity in the worke of the Lord,</hi> ſloth, and negligence, is a contemptible thing, and makes men vile and odious. Labour alſo to adorne it with <hi>holineſſe of life</hi> and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; without which the other are no more but as a pearle in the head of a filthy toade: a pearle in the head, and the body all poiſon, for men to have good and able parts, but ſtinking and rotten lives, ready to poiſon every one with the report of them; that is not the way to maintain the honour of the miniſtery. Labour therefore for an vpright life, and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which will bee a great credit and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the office of the miniſtery, it growes to bee deſpicable, when there is a failing in this, and a man in the want of it, doth but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade himſelfe of the honour due to the office.</p>
                  <p>This might alſo bee a caveat to all <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">4. <hi>Candidato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
                     </note> to thoſe that are to <hi>enter upon the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> eſpecially to ſuch as are every way <hi>vnfit and vnworthy</hi> for it: doe you deſpiſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable place of the miniſtery, that you will bee ready to thruſt your ſelues into it, before God calls you, and their be worth in you to fit you for it? take heed of this, for elſe it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7995:43"/> will bee your great ſinne, and your exceeding ſhame.</p>
                  <p>This may bee a good <hi>Jtem</hi> to the <hi>people,</hi> in a word, to teach them what <hi>apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> they ſhould have <hi>concerning the Miniſters,</hi> that they would acknowledge <hi>this honour,</hi> and <hi>carry themſelues</hi> accordingly, and there be 3. things I will mention.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, It is fit, that the people ſhould give <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> them <hi>honourable reſpect,</hi> in ſuch a proportion as is meet, an <hi>honourable countenance</hi> is due to them that are in an honourable place.</p>
                  <p>Secondly an <hi>honourable maintenance</hi> is as due, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> it is a vaine thing to ſet a man high in reſpect, and to ſtarve a man in his meanes.</p>
                  <p>There is an honour of <hi>Maintenance,</hi> as well as of <hi>Countenance,</hi> and it is impoſſible the repute of the Miniſter ſhould be kept up, without an honourable maintenance. It hath beene ſaid of ſome of the City, that their manner is to <hi>deale with their Miniſters,</hi> as <hi>Carryers</hi> doe with their horſes, to lay heavy burthens upon them, exact worke enough; but they ſhall have but <hi>eaſie commons,</hi> and then to recompence this, they ſhall have bells hung about their necks, they ſhall be commended and applauded high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for excellent Miniſters, and great paines-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, but good words will not fill hungry bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, nor cover naked backes, nor fit a ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with a Library. But that no man may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake me. I know there is no worthy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7995:43"/> but abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es the thought of this, there is no <hi>noble Citizen,</hi> but is farre from ſuch a kind of carriage, yet you know there may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy cullions whoſe practice is ſuch, <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hoggiſh Gaderens,</hi> that wil be ready to grutch and grumble at the expence of a penny, for the maintenance of the divine candle, that waſteth it ſelfe to give light unto them, that will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther die to ſave charges, then ſpend money to ſave their lives. It is a ſaying, that he that needs the lampe will not grutch to give oyle to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: but yet many there are who had rather live in the <hi>ſhadow of death,</hi> then bee at coſt to preſerve the <hi>light of life.</hi> I have heard it hath beene obſerved by ſome, as an unquall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in Miniſters, who will plead earneſtly, for their owne dues, and yet deny God his: Some have obſerved this as an unequall kinde of carriage, but I may tell you it is unequall to force Miniſters to plead for their right untill they bee hoarſe, even then when they ſhould be giving of God his due, and the people theirs: but I ſuppoſe there is no reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man, but will thinke that an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maintenance is due to an honourable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly. There is an <hi>honour of obedience,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſervice, which is the chiefeſt of all, if they be in an honourable place, then whatſoever they do by vertue of their commiſſion, ſuch as they have good warrant for from God, take heed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7995:44"/> how any man <hi>kicke or ſpurne</hi> againſt them, but let us ſay as <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Peter, Loe we are all here ready to heare all things that are commanded thee of God.</hi> We muſt looke up unto God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as he layes the charge upon the miniſtery and ſo we muſt take our charge from them, and yeeld obedience anſwerably.</p>
                  <p>To adde a word or two by way of motive. It is not becauſe I would plead my owne cauſe <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> or the cauſe of others, that are of my coate, for I doe not frequently harpe upon theſe ſtrings, neither doe I complaine; for honour, God hath given mee more then my expectation, and for maintenance, ſufficient according to my deſire. So that it is not for any private reſpect to my ſelf. But the motives I deſire to commend unto you, are in reſpect of your ſelves. Two things I ſhall but mention.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of all conſider it is <hi>a great ſinne,</hi> not to give the miniſters of God, thoſe honourable reſpects of obſervance, and obedience, as is meete to doe. It is <hi>a ſinne againſt God.</hi> And <hi>a ſin againſt a mans ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſinne againſt God, the injury and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that is done to any of the meſſengers, and ambaſſadours of God, reflects upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, God takes it as done to himſelfe, it being done to his miniſters and meſſengers. So that in this reſpect, we ſhall be found <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be fighters againſt God himſelfe. And as it is a ſin againſt God;</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:44"/>
                  <p>So it is a <hi>ſinne againſt our ſelves,</hi> you are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in moſt injurious to your ſelues, for by this meanes you <hi>hinder the efficacy,</hi> and powerfull working of the Miniſtery of the word upon your owne ſoules, there is no greater impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and checking buſines to hinder the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of good from any miniſter, then when a man is anticipated with baſe, and meane, &amp; low conceits of him, if men contemne their perſons or their callings, and give them not the honour in their hearts which is due to them, it is a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty let and impediment, of their improvement and advantage in goodnes, by their miniſtery. So that it is a ſin againſt God, and a ſin againſt our ſelves, but then</p>
                  <p>Doe but conſider, <hi>what will be the end and iſſue of ſinne,</hi> ſin owes a man a ſpight, and will pay <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> him home one day. God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll not ſuffer ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed: Eſpecially a ſinne of this nature, that ſtrikes, and reflects ſo upon himſelfe, hee hath ſaid, <hi>touch not mine annointed, and doe my prophets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o harme,</hi> if we therefore faile in this duty, God will not faile to meete with us for it another day. It is reported, that <hi>Rome</hi> was deſtroyed to the ground, for ſome abuſes that were offred to an Ambaſſadour that was ſent unto it. And <hi>David</hi> we know never played any ſuch harſh play in all his life, as he did to the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> that deſpitefully uſed his Ambaſſadours, which he ſent unto them, <hi>when they ſhaved their heards and cut their coates,</hi> let us take heed of abuſing the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7995:45"/> meſſengers of God, of cutting their coates in any kind, of cutting them ſhort of their tythes as ſome doe that allow not them needfull main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, even ſo much as is for neceſſity, that if the miniſters themſelues ſhould cut their coates according to their cloath, they muſt be forced to goe in part naked. Let us take heed of this, as alſo give unto them, all <hi>due reſpects of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and obedience</hi> as is meete, for if we do not doe it, we ſinne againſt God, and God will not put up at our hands the indignities we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to thoſe who are under his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, that are his meſſengers, and Ambaſſadours, God will take it highly, and puniſh it hainouſly.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:45"/>
                  <p>BARUCH'S SORE GENTLY OPENED: GOD'S SALVE SKILFVLLY APPLIED: In two SERMONS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY</hi> JOHN STOUGHTON, Doctor in Divinity, ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Immanuel Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> late of <hi>Aldermanburie,</hi> LONDON.</p>
                  <p>AMOS 5. 14. <hi>Seeke good, and not evill, that you may live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie, Henry Overton, Iohn Rothwell,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith.</hi> 1640.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7995:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
